# Dr. Micheline Campbell

Scientist, QLD Dept. of Natural Resources, Mines, and Energy Rockhampton, Australia
☐ +61 411 282 657
☑ michelineleecampbell@gmail.com
☑ michcampbell\_
☑ MichelineCampbell

# Professional Summary

I have a PhD in palaeo-climatology and am currently working in hydrological sediment and nutrient transport. I have strong data science skills and have developed research skills applicable to a broad range of topics within the environmental sciences. My PhD research focused on stalagmite-based climate proxy records and associated karst geomorphology and groundwater hydrology, while my current position with the Queensland Department of Natural Resources, Mining, and Energy has a strong focus on field experiments and hypothesis testing with the aim of reducing nutrient and sediment runoff to Great Barrier Reef catchments. I am hoping to further my scientific career by securing a position where I can continue to use the skills I have developed, broaden my skillset, and return to teaching and engaging with undergraduate and postgraduate students.

# Education

- Aug 2014 PhD (Geography), Agriculture and Environment, The University of Western Jul 2019 Australia, Perth, Western Australia, Australia.
  - $\circ$  Thesis: Speleothem-based palaeo-climate research: Methodology, applications, and insight from the Snowy Mountains, southeast Australia
  - o Supervisors: JN. Callow, H. McGowan, G.McGrath, H. Wong
- Jul 2013 **BA** (Hons, 1st Class) (Geography), Geography, Planning, and Environ-Jun 2014 mental Management, The University of Queensland, Brisbane, QLD, Australia.
  - o Thesis: The Drip Hydrology of a Speleothem from the Yarrangobilly Caves, NSW, Australia
  - o Supervisors: H. Mcgowan, JN. Callow
- Feb 2010 **BA (Geography and Spanish)**, The University of Queensland, Brisbane, Dec 2012 QLD, Australia.

# Experience

## Research

- Feb 2020 **Scientist**, Land and Water Science Unit, QLD Dept. of Natural Resources, present Mining and Energy, Rockhampton, QLD, Australia.
  - o Analysed cane trash trial data.
  - o Found that there a significant proportion of the variation of sediment in cane paddock runoff can be described by soil type and cane trash cover.

- Aug 2019 **Research Assistant**, School of Agriculture and Environment, University of Dec 2019 Western Australia, Perth, WA, Australia.
  - o Miscellaneous data analysis tasks
- Aug 2014 PhD Researcher, School of Agriculture and Environment, University of West-Jul 2019 ern Australia, Perth, WA, Australia.
  - o Developed two new palaeo-climate proxy records for south east Australia
  - o Showed that the climate of the LIG has similar significant periodicities, suggesting our long term climate patterns (e.g. PDO) will continue as temperatures increase with climate change.
  - Used social network analysis to advance our understanding of methodologies applied in the speleothem palaeo-climate proxy community and the development of the field over time.
  - o Demonstrated that LA-ICP-MS and LA-ICP-AES of trace elements in speleothem calcite produce comparable results

## Teaching

- 2019 Course Co-Coordinator and Lecturer: Catchment and River Processes, School of Agriculture and Environment, The University of Western Australia, Perth, WA, Australia.
- 2018 **Tutor:** Geographies of a Global City, School of Agriculture and Enviroment, The University of Western Australia, Perth, WA, Australia.
- 2014–2019 **Tutor: Catchment and River Processes**, School of Agriculture and Enviroment, The University of Western Australia, Perth, WA, Australia.

Teaching contributions include the delivery and creation of content for undergraduate and masters level units, both in the classroom/laboratory and in the field. Catchment and River Processes, which I have taught into since its inception at UWA, has consistently achieved high student ratings, including in 2018 when it received a score of 3.7/4. This placed it in the 70th percentile of UWA courses.

# Funding and Scholarships

- 2018 Australian Institute of Nuclear Science and Engineering Travel grant. \$1000
- 2017 Australian and New Zealand Geomorphological Group Travel grant. \$300
- 2016 University of Western Australia Travel grant. \$1850
- 2015–2018 Australian Institute of Nuclear Science and Engineering Postgraduate Ressarch Award Stipend. \$7500pa
- 2015–2018 Australian Institute of Nuclear Science and Engineering Postgraduate Ressarch Award Analytical Budget. \$1000pa
- 2014–2018 Australian Government Research Training Program Stipend. \$26000pa
- 2014–2015~ Snowy Hydro Ltd. Stipend.  $\$5000\mathrm{pa}$ 
  - 2014 University of Western Australia Stipend. \$3000

# Publications

#### Published

- 1. Campbell, M, J Callow, G McGrath, and H McGowan (May 2018). Co-authorship analysis of the speleothem proxy-climate community: working together to tackle the big problems. *International Journal of Speleology* 47(2), 165–172.
- 2. McGowan, H, JN Callow, J Soderholm, G McGrath, M Campbell, and Jx Zhao (Dec. 2018). Global warming in the context of 2000 years of Australian alpine temperature and snow cover. *Scientific Reports* 8(1), 4394.
- 3. Campbell, M, JN Callow, G McGrath, and H McGowan (Dec. 2017). A multimethod approach to inform epikarst drip discharge modelling: Implications for palaeo-climate reconstruction. *Hydrological Processes* **31**(26), 4734–4747.

#### In Review

1. McGowan, H, M Campbell, JN Callow, A Lowry, and H Wong (In Review). Evidence of multi-decadal wet-dry cycles and mega-droughts in the Eemian warm climate epoch, southeast Australia.

### In Preparation

- 1. Campbell, M and H Wong (In Preparation). LA-ICP-AES to analyse trace elements in speleothems.
- 2. Campbell, M, JN Callow, H McGowan, H Wong, and G McGrath (In Preparation). Solar forcing of mid-latitude terrestrial hydroclimate over the past 6.5 ka.

# Conference Presentations

#### Talks

Feb 2017 A geophysical approach to inform epikarst drip discharge modelling: Implications for palaeo-climate reconstruction, Australian and New Zealand Geomorphological Group 17th Biennial Conference, Greytown, New Zealand, Campbell, M., Callow, J.N., McGrath, G.S., McGowan, H.A. 2016.

#### Posters

- Apr 2018 Climate patterns in South-east Australia: the Last Interglacial vs. the last 2K, 20th EGU General Assembly, Vienna, Austria, Campbell, M., Callow, J.N., McGowan, H.A., McGrath, G.S., Wong, H.
- Feb 2017 First Insights of the Eemian Hydroclimate of the Snowy Mountains, Australia, Australian and New Zealand Geomorphological Group 17th Biennial Conference, Greytown, New Zealand, Campbell, M., Wong, H., McGrath, G.S., McGowan, H.A., Callow, J.N.
- Dec 2016 First Insights of the Eemian Hydroclimate of the Snowy Mountains, Australia, American Geophysical Union, Fall Meeting, San Francisco, USA, Campbell, M. Wong, H., McGrath, G.S., McGowan, H.A., Callow, J.N..

# Skills

#### Statistical

#### Statistical Software.

- o R (advanced)
- o Python (fundamental awareness)

#### Statistical Methods.

- o Time series analysis
- o Hypothesis testing
- o Social network analysis
- o Linear models
- o Generalised linear models
- o Numerical modelling

#### Field

# Surveying.

- o Total station
- o Real time kinematic

## Electrical Resistivity Tomography.

- o Deployment
- o Data processing and analysis

## Environmental Data Loggers.

- o Onset HOBO
- o In-Situ Rugged Troll
- o Driptych Stalagmate

## Soil profile and sampling protocol.

#### Water sampling.

- o Isotopes
- o Nutrients

#### Other

#### Software.

- o ArcGIS (novice)
- o Microsoft Suite (advanced)
- o LaTEX (novice)
- o Rmarkdown(fundamental awareness)

## Service

# Aug 2017 - Participant, Science in Schools Program.

Aug 2017 o Travelled to a regional town to share some love for science with primary school kids

# Feb 2015 - Postgraduate representative to the School of Earth and Environment.

Jul 2017 o Led the organisation of 2 annual symposia for postgraduate students within the school.

- o Reported student concerns to the School administration
- o Support and troubleshooting for new students

- Mar 2016 Co-Convenor, SEE LearnR Workshop.
  - Jan 2016 o Organised a short series of 'Introduction to R' courses for the students and staff of the School of Earth and Environment
- Oct 2014 Guest presenter, ENVT2221: Global Climate Change and Oct 2014 Biodiversity.
  - o Presented 'Palaeo-climate and Stalagmites' for 2nd-year Biology students at UWA

# Professional Development

- 2020 Advanced R Workshop, The University of Queensland, Australia.
- 2020 Intermediate R Workshop, The University of Queensland, Australia.
- 2018 Weathering Climate Change: How have humans coped with climate change-and how will we continue to do so?, The University of Western Australia, Australia.
- 2018 Masterclass in Creating Opportunities and Developing your Research Skills, The University of Western Australia, Australia.
- 2016 Synthesis II From dynamics of structure to function of complex networks, TU Dresden, Germany.
- 2016 Water on Earth: origin, reservoirs, and its global cycle, The University of Western Australia, Australia.
- 2016 Research Bazaar, Murdoch University, Australia.
- 2016 Fundamentals of the analysis of networks, The University of Western Australia, Australia.
- 2014 Writing and publishing in scientific journals, The University of Western Australia, Australia.

Referees